Charlotte Lowe Bryan papers, 1873-1948 C46
Indiana University Archives
Charlotte Lowe Bryan papers
1873-1948
Indiana University Archives
Bryan, Charlotte Lowe, 1867-1948
C46
.6 cubic feet
Charlotte A. Lowe, born September 7, 1867, in Indianapolis, Indiana, was the wife of William Lowe Bryan. The collection consists of personal papers, correspondence, and writings of Charlotte Lowe Bryan in four series: American Association of University Women, 1932-1933, consisting of loan fund reports for the Bloomington chapter; Addresses and presentations, 1929-1937, containing copies of speeches given both by and for Bryan; Correspondence, 1873-1937, containing correspondence both to and from Bryan; and Publications, 1933-1937, consisting of typescripts and galley sheets of articles written by Bryan.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Charlotte A. Lowe was born September 7, 1867, in Indianapolis, Indiana. She attended elementary and high school in Indianapolis and graduated second in her class from Shortridge High School in 1885. She entered Indiana University and graduated with an A.B. in Greek in 1888. In a letter by then-President David Starr Jordan, he wrote, "Her rank in college was the very highest--in many studies higher than any other woman who has graduated from the University." Lowe continued her studies and received her Master of Arts in 1889.
That same year, Lowe also married William J. Bryan, who changed his name to William Lowe Bryan in her honor. In 1902, WLB assumed the presidency of Indiana University, a position he held until 1937. Although quite ill throughout most of her husband's presidency, Charlotte remained an active member of the University community in her role of "First Lady." In addition to numerous other projects and involvements, Charlotte oversaw the design and construction of the Bryan House, which still serves as the President's home on campus today. Charlotte Lowe Bryan died on August 26, 1948.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: American Association of University Women, Addresses and presentations, Correspondence, and Publications.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Charlotte Lowe Bryan are organized into four series: American Association of University Women, 1932-1933; Addresses and presentation, 1929-1937; Correspondence, 1873-1937; and Publications, 1933-1937.
The American Association of University Women series is small, consisting of only one folder. It is made up of Loan fund reports of the organization.
The Addresses and presentations series includes copies of speeches and presentations both given by and for Bryan, many of them containing Bryan's handwritten notes. The folders are arranged alphabetically.
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence series is by far the largest series, containing correspondence both to and from Bryan spanning 1873 to 1948. Additionally, the Lowe family folder contains notes about the Lowe family, including genealogical information. The correspondence from Lora Webster, Janet Ramsay Sims, Elizabeth Pennington, "Nettie", Alice Moore, Mrs. Carl Franzeu and H. E. Cowan are voluminous.
The journal kept by "Lotta" is from 1879, and it is complete and detailed.
In the Publications series, typescripts and galley sheets of articles written by Bryan can be found. Many of them contain handwritten corrections and notes by Bryan. The folders are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
William Lowe Bryan papers, 1830-1956, Collection C69.
Acquisition Information
Accession 1149
College presidents' spouses --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; College presidents' spouses --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Indiana University; Indiana University -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Bryan, William Lowe, 1860-1955 -- Correspondence; American Association of University Women. Bloomington Branch (Ind.) -- Archives; American Association of University Women. Bloomington Branch (Ind.) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indiana University -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; American Association of University Women. Bloomington Branch (Ind.); Bryan, Charlotte Lowe, 1867-1948 -- Correspondence; Bryan, Charlotte Lowe, 1867-1948 -- Archives; Bryan, William Lowe, 1860-1955 -- Archives; Bryan, William Lowe, 1860-1955 -- Correspondence -- Selections
- American Association of University Women, 1932-1933
  - Loan Fund Reports, 1932-1933 (Box 1)
- Addresses and presentations, 1929-1937
  - Alumnae Breakfast, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Meeting, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Commencement, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Dedication - Forest Hall, undated (Box 1)
  - Presentation of portrait by class of 1918, undated (Box 1)
  - Speech given at dinner in honor of Dr. Bryan and herself, 1937 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1873-1937
  - A, 1933-1936 (Box 1)
  - B, undated (Box 1)
  - Barnes, A.R., 1935 (Box 1)
  - "Bettie", 1941 (Box 1)
  - Bryan, E. A., 1938-1940 (Box 1)
  - Bryan, William Lowe, 1936-1948 (Box 1)
  - Carter, Nell Fulton, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Chamness, Ivy, undated (Box 1)
  - "Classmates", 1941-1948 (Box 1)
  - Cowan, H. E., 1941-1948 (Box 1)
  - Craven, Ruth, undated (Box 1)
  - Cravens, Mellie G., 1941 (Box 1)
  - D, 1933-1948 (Box 1)
  - Dever, Elizabeth, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Fesler, Bert, 8 June 1936 (Box 1)
  - Fesler, James W., 26 November 1933 (Box 1)
  - Franzeu, Mrs. Carl, 1934-1938 (Box 1)
  - French Lick Springs Hotel, 1935 (Box 1)
  - G, 1933 (Box 1)
  - H, 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - Hardery, Maude Cole, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Howard, Joe, 1941-1947 (Box 1)
  - Howard, Mrs. Robert L., 1947 (Box 1)
  - "Jackie", 1941-1947 (Box 1)
  - Jordan, David Starr, 1888 (Box 1)
  - "Professor Judson", undated (Box 1)
  - K, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Kirklin, O.L., 1935 (Box 1)
  - L, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Lewis, Evageline E., 1941-1948 (Box 1)
  - Lowe family, c.1873-1929 (Box 1)
  - McNutt, Ruth J., 1922-1923; 1935 (Box 1)
  - Masters, Robert J., 1933 (Box 1)
  - Matthews, B.F., 1948 (Box 1)
  - Miller, Albert, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Miller, Idelle B., 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Mixau?, Nell S., 1947 (Box 1)
  - Moore, Alice, 1941-1947 (Box 1)
  - "Nettie", 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - Nineteenth Century Club, undated (Box 1)
  - Pennington, Elizabeth, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Phillips, Mary Belle, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Piercy, Josephine, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Pitkin, Mary V., 1947 (Box 1)
  - R, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Rabb, Frances, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Ramsey, Clara, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Rich, Claude, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Robbins, Hilda S., 1947 (Box 1)
  - Saks, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Schacht, C. T. Oscar, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Schuman, Edith B., undated (Box 1)
  - Sheneer(?), Mary M., 1941; undated (Box 1)
  - Siebert, Raymond E., 1940 (Box 1)
  - Sims, Janet Ramsay, 1941-1948 (Box 1)
  - Smith, ?, undated (Box 1)
  - Spencer, Eleanor R., 1947 (Box 1)
  - T, 1940-1947 (Box 1)
  - Teter, Bill and Nellie, undated (Box 1)
  - Webster, Lora, 1941-1948 (Box 1)
  - Westenhauer, Lula M., 1941 (Box 1)
  - White-Haines Optical Co., 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Wiecking, Janet, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Willis, Hugh E., 1941 (Box 1)
  - General, undated; 1941 (Box 1)
  - Fragments, envelopes, undated (Box 1)
- Journal, 1879
  - Journal, 1879 (Box 1)
- Publications, 1933-1937
  - A Poet Comes to Dine, undated (Box 1)
  - Truth and Fiction, 1937 (Box 1)
  - What are You Eating Now?, undated (Box 1)
  - When We were Tramps, 1933 (Box 1)